<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Daily Notes</title><link>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/</link><description>My daily notes</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://dailynote.simulkade.com/rss.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 19:16:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Daily notes - 2017-06-02</title><link>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-06-02-daily-notes.html</link><dc:creator>AA Eftekhari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Early in the morning, I did some computations by assuming that the injection rate is equal to the water cut and the injection pressure is around the hydrostatic pressure. Depending on the water cut, the recovery factor can be indeed negative but only for very high water cuts (99% plus)&lt;br&gt;
I was thinking about using Reaktoro to estimate the enthalpy of reaction at different temperatures and then fit the correlation that is used in phreeqc for the enthalpy of reaction to the Reaktoro HKF estimations. I'll have to do it later.&lt;br&gt;
I just contacted a seller on Reshopper to buy a bike trailer seat for Aidin.&lt;br&gt;
I'm trying to rewrite a piece of code that I have written many times previously, but for some reason, I cannot focus today.&lt;br&gt;
I sent an email that I should have sent a couple of weeks ago, and although the reply was not favorable, it made me feel less anxious.&lt;br&gt;
My code finally works and it is fast enough. I do not have enough energy to finish my work today, anyway.&lt;br&gt;
I have realized that my problem is not procrastination alone. My other problem is laziness. Don't get me wrong! I'm not comparing myself to the really lazy people, but to real hardworking scientists like Hans. I have to try and force my brain to work harder and longer.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-06-02-daily-notes.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 08:03:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Daily notes - 1 June 2017</title><link>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-06-01-daily-notes.html</link><dc:creator>AA Eftekhari</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm in the library and this is my plan for today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the recovery data from the data base&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write an objective function based on the Buckley-Leverett formulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the optimization problem in Julia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize the rel-perm parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny story: the paper that has done core flooding and reported the recovery data at high temperature, does not report the viscosity of oil at high temperature. I had to calculate it using this correlation:
$$\ln(\frac{\mu}{\mu_0}) = B(\frac{1}{T}-\frac{1}{T_0})$$
I found the B value by fitting the above equation to the viscosity data of n-Dodecane. The viscosity data comes from the cool &lt;a href="http://www.coolprop.org"&gt;CoolProp&lt;/a&gt; package.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recovery data is not a straight line at the beginning of the core flooding. It must be a problem in choosing the right moment to start the timer. I shifted the curve to make it consistent.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important problem with using the analytical solution of the BL equation as an objective function is that very occasionally, the shock front cannot be found with a reasonable numerical accuracy. This blows up the objective function and the whole optimization procedure. Perhaps, I should try the numerical solution (upwind) that is slower, but (almost) always converges.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-06-01-daily-notes.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 06:34:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2017-05-31 daily notes</title><link>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-05-31-daily-notes.html</link><dc:creator>AA Eftekhari</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have decided to write whatever comes to my mind every day.&lt;br&gt;
Writing the paper on the exergy analysis of geothermal energy, and thinking about the methane carbon emission and specific exergy. The chemical exergy of methane comes from the sun, which is of course clear since we don't have any other energy source (well perhaps geothermal and nuclear are different unless. Unless we are debris of the sun?). Anyway, the funny part is that what we burn now as fossil fuel is the sunshine of millions of years ago that is stored underground. Wood is the sunshine of several years ago. Wind and waves are the sunshine of few days ago perhaps? I'm not sure.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm thinking about getting the temperature history for, e.g., last year to calculate the heat loss from a building block and use it to estimate the energy requirement for warming. These are some of the usefull links I have found so far. I will go through them later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.earthsystemcog.org/projects/openclimategis/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;http://icclim.readthedocs.io/en/latest/python_api.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://github.com/cerfacs-globc/icclim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/cdo-web/#t=secondTabLink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://www.wunderground.com/weather/api/d/docs?d=data/history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https://github.com/csparpa/pyowm  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also looked into the bicycle trailers (fietskar in Dutch or Cykeltrailer in Danish) to find out whether it is possible to use one to carry Aidin around. Apparently, there is a small seat that can be installed inside a trailer for newborns.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote two more pages of our paper. The mathematical modeling section is now complete. Tomorrow I'll work on the results and discussion and then hopefully before the end of the week I can take care of the introduction and send it away.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'm going home to have a cup of coffee (decaf), play with Aidin, and work on another paper if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://dailynote.simulkade.com/posts/2017-05-31-daily-notes.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 06:57:10 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>